Guide to the Goldie Krantz Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Goldie Krantz papers
1928-1977
MS 780
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(20 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, research memoranda, addresses, publications, and miscellaneous biographical material of Goldie Krantz, an active proponent of prepaid dental and medical care. In addition, there are records concerning the Welfare Fund of the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, the Pacific Maritime Association, and the Group Health Association. Memoranda and other papers related to her work as a researcher and consultant in evaluating health care plans in various parts of the United States are also included. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Krantz, Goldie, 1915-1976
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lorin E. Kerr, 1977.
Arrangement
Arranged in seven series: I. Correspondence. II. Research and Consultation. III. Addresses and Publications. IV. Teaching. V. War Shipping Administration. VI. Biography and Memorabilia. VII. Health Plan Publication.
Scope and Contents
The Goldie Krantz Papers consist of twenty boxes of correspondence, speeches, memorabilia, and miscellaneous working papers arranged in seven series.
There are items related to almost every period of her education and career, but many of her accomplishments are virtually unrepresented. Especially disappointing is the scanty documentation of her work in organizing programs for the ILWU-PMA Welfare Fund.
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, consists mainly of letters that Goldie Krantz herself classified as "personal" when she organized her files at the Welfare Fund and the Group Health Association. Almost all her correspondents were professionally interested in public health, and the majority of the letters are concerned with prepaid medical or dental care, but there are few extended discussions or exchanges of views. The historical value of the letters lies mainly in scattered lines and passages: Krantz revealed her politics and her personality even in routine correspondence, and comments on professional business that are more tantalizing than instructive when read in isolation may assume some importance in the context of information garnered from the papers of other individuals and organizations. There are seldom more than a few incoming letters filed under any one name, but the volume is more impressive when one considers how many of her correspondents were staff members of the Kaiser Foundation Health Plan, the San Joaquin Foundation for Medical Care, the ILWU-PMA Welfare Fund, the Pacific Maritime Association, or the Group Health Association. The best documentation of her regular responsibilities as Welfare Fund Secretary is in her correspondence with her successor, Anne Waybur (whose title was Administrator), in the first year after she left the position. There is also important professional correspondence interspersed with other material in Series II.
Series II, RESEARCH AND CONSULTATION, contains miscellaneous working papers created by Goldie Krantz and her associates in the course of developing and evaluating health care programs. There is a separate section for each project.
The section on Hawaii Dental Plan is related to Krantz's trip to the Islands in 1962 to assist the Hawaii Employers Council and ILWU Local 142 in negotiating prepaid dental care for union members' children. The only information about the service she rendered comes from a newspaper clipping and from letters of appreciation.
The section on ILWU-PMA Benefit Funds Contract Renewal is related to negotiations in various West Coast ports in 1965 to renew the contract between the union and the employers' association. The papers consist mainly of circular letters, memoranda, and draft agreements sent to Krantz by staff members of the Benefit Funds and the PMA. This material would be helpful in reconstructing the negotiations if the records of the primary participants were not available, but none of the items originated with Goldie Krantz, and her advisory role must be inferred from brief remarks in covering letters.
The section titled Hospital Admission Study is related to a research project designed to discover why federal employees who combined Blue Cross-Blue Shield insurance with recourse to independent practitioners used more hospital services than those who subscribed to the Group Health Association. ¹ Goldie Krantz was one of six principal investigators. Her assignment was to be "responsible for data acquisition and coordination at GHA" and to serve "in a policy role with the project" (minutes, 1970 Jul 7-8), and the papers in this section furnish many examples of both kinds of activity. Her contribution is shown in letters to other participants, memoranda for fellow employees of the GHA, notes on conversations for her own files, and a critique of a draft report on the first phase of the study.
Besides the documentation of the study itself, several of Krantz's writings in this section reveal something about the politics of medical care. In a memorandum to the Executive Director of the GHA, she explained that a grant from the federal government to finance the research was being delayed by political pressure (1969 Nov 21). A year later, she noted dissension among the participants and complained that the GHA was not receiving full representation (1970 Sep 16). And when the report on the first phase of the study was being prepared, she rallied opposition to the proposal that the Blue Cross Association publish it instead of leaving that role to an organization that was not a subject of the investigation (1973 Oct 11).
he section titled Mental Health Study furnishes a detailed technical record of an investigation of the utilization of psychiatric services provided by the Group Health Association. ² The research and analysis were conducted between 1968 and 1973 under contract with the National Institute of Mental Health, and Krantz's principal collaborators were members of the Institute staff. Her own role is well documented in letters and memoranda, but students of her ideas and methods may learn more from the preceding section because the problems addressed here are relatively narrow.
Group Health Cooperative of Puget Sound consists mainly of correspondence initiated by staff members of the Group, Health Association to help them discover why the Seattle area program differed radically from their own in the cost and utilization of services.
The section on the Advisory Committee on Dental Health is related to the work of a panel of seventeen authorities on dental care who were appointed in 1970 to advise the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. Goldie Krantz was the only member not identified as "Dr.," and she was designated the Public Representative. The working papers and draft reports that make up this section were produced in multiple copies for general distribution to the members, and there is no means of isolating her contribution. The product of the committee's work was its Report and Recommendations to the Secretary, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare(1972).
The section on the Medical Care Foundation of Sacramento is related to Krantz's employment by the Foundation as a consultant in 1972 and 1974. The principal example of her work is a critique of a proposed contract between the Foundation Community Health Plan and Blue Cross of Northern California for a pilot project involving a joint offering of health care services (1974 Aug 12).
The section on the American Public Health Association has notes and correspondence connected with Krantz's service as chairman of the Nominating Committee of the Medical Care Section in 1975.
Series III, ADDRESSES AND PUBLICATIONS, contains most of Goldie Krantz's published articles, a few of her addresses to professional organizations, and a transcript of a meeting of the California Governor's Committee on the Study of Medical Aid and Health in which she participated.
Series IV, TEACHING, contains notes, printed matter, and mimeographed handouts for some of Krantz's lectures on the organization and financing of health care at the University of California School of Dentistry and Howard University College of Medicine.
Series V, WAR SHIPPING ADMINISTRATION, contains more than a dozen unrelated items that have some bearing on Krantz's employment with the Manning and Recruitment Organization (MRO). The most important are these: an outline and report on the MRO and a memorandum on reconversion, all possibly her own work; a transcript of a radio broadcast in which she was interviewed about her job; a script for a radio broadcast dramatizing her experience in wartime shipping; and a transcript of a "routine" FBI interrogation in which she denied past and present association with the Communist party. On the last subject, see also Series VI.
Series VI, BIOGRAPHY AND MEMORABILIA, contains miscellaneous items related to Goldie Krantz's education, career, and personal life. The papers of greatest biographical value are these: university class notes with comments on the poor quality of the teaching; a student essay beginning "I am a Communist…"; numerous resumés, some with detailed job descriptions; political leaflets from the mid-1950s; letters to businesses praising and criticizing their services and staff; and clippings from medical journals with critical annotations. There are also photographs and personal mementoes.
Series VII, HEALTH PLAN PUBLICATIONS, contains brochures, annual reports, and miscellaneous printed matter produced by unions, clinics, and other organizations concerned with prepaid dental and medical care.
¹ The results of the first phase of research are presented in Donald C. Riedel, Antone G. Singsen, Daniel C. Walden, Samuel Meyers, Goldie Krantz, and Marie Henderson,Federal Employees Health Benefits Program Utilization Study, United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, Health Resources Administration, DHEW publication no. (HRA) 75-3125 (1975).
² Results of the pilot study are presented in Irving D. Goldberg, Goldie Krantz, and Ben Z. Locke, "Effect of a Short-term Outpatient Psychiatric Therapy Benefit on the Utilization of Medical Services in a Prepaid Group Practice Program,"Medical Care, V (1970), 419-428.
Biographical / Historical
Goldie Krantz was a nationally recognized authority on prepaid dental and medical care with a long record of accomplishment in advocacy, planning, and administration. Her career in public health began in 1950, when she joined the staff of the ILWU-PMA Welfare Fund (later incorporated in the ILWU-PMA Benefit Funds), an agency responsible for administering the health benefits provided in the contract between the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union and the Pacific Maritime Association. As Secretary of the Fund from 1950 to 1962, she monitored purchase and utilization of services and organized or helped organize programs in comprehensive medical care, multiphasic screening, and dental care for children. In 1962 she became Program Analyst for the Group Health Association, a prepaid group health care plan in Washington, D.C., and she remained in that position until her retirement in 1975.
In addition to her employment with these organizations, she served as consultant to the U.S. Public Health Service (1955-1962) and the Pacific Maritime Association (1962-1968); lectured at several universities; spoke at numerous meetings of medical, dental, and public health associations; and published many articles in professional journals.
These achievements are all the more remarkable because Krantz began her career in prepaid medical and dental care without training or experience in public health. Indeed, her work in that field occupied only two-thirds of her professional life. Having graduated from the University of Minnesota in 1934, she was employed for several years as a social worker in Minnesota public welfare agencies, where she quickly rose to positions of responsibility. After attending classes in public administration at the University of California in 1939, she began work as an economist with the Pacific Coast Labor Bureau, a private agency that represented trade unions in bargaining with government agencies. Soon after transferring to the Bureau's Washington office in 1942, she took a position with the Manning and Recruitment Organization of the War Shipping Administration, serving first as an economist and then as an administrator. She left this position in 1946, shortly before the birth of her daughter, Rebecca, and her next employment was with the Welfare Fund.
Goldie Krantz was survived by her fourth husband, Dr. Lorin E. Kerr.
The Goldie Krantz Papers were given to Yale University Library by Lorin E. Kerr in 1977. Seven cartons of printed matter were separated from the papers for distribution to other departments of the Library. Most of these were concerned with public health, but there were also some political items, which are listed in the Appendix.
Communists -- United States; Dental care -- United States; Dental insurance; Health insurance -- United States; Working class; Medical care -- United States; Medicine; Mental health services -- United States; Public health; Labor union welfare funds -- United States; Women in medicine; Women; Health services administrators; Health-officers; Labor movement; Labor; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Abrams, Herbert Kerman, 1913-; Brewster, Agnes Wharton, 1908-; Goodenough, Benton H.; Kerr, Lorin E., 1909-; Krantz, Goldie, 1915-1976; Letson, Edward W.; McCarthy, Denis J. (Denis Joseph), 1939-; Pelton, Walter J.; Root, Chester L.; St. Sure, J. Paul; Waybur, Ann; Weissman, Arthur, 1913-; California. Department of Public Health; United States. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare; United States. War Shipping Administration; American Public Health Association; Blue Cross Association; Bureau of Social Science Research (Washington, D.C.); Group Health Association of America; Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union and Pacific Maritime Association; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union and Pacific Maritime Association. Welfare Fund; Kaiser Foundation Health Plan; Pacific Maritime Association; San Joaquin Foundation for Medical Care; United Mine Workers of America
- Correspondence, 1950-1975; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The arrangement is alphabetical.
  Folders with asterisks(*) contain ten or more items
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abrams, Herbert L. (*), 1956-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Health Systems (*), 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anderson, Odin, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ashe, Pocahontas Y., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Associated Appraisers of Impaired Earning Capacity
    General
    See: box 1, folder 20
  - Axelrod, Solomon J., 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - B (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bailey, Richard M., 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bellaire Clinic, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Berkov, Bernard V., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bodine, Howard J., 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bodine, Howard J., 1962 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Borhani, Nemat O., 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brand, Morris, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Breslow, Lester, [1964?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brewster, Agnes W. (Mrs. Vernon H.) (*), 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bridges, Harry, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bridges, Nikki, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brown, Hubert, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brown, Wallace L.C., 1962-1963, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - California, Department of Public Health (*), 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    See also: box 1, folder 5
    See also: box 1, folder 6
  - California, University of, 1956, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Centerville Clinic, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Committee for National Health Insurance, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Committee to Evaluate the National Center for Health Statistics, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commonwealth Club (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Community Group Health Foundation, Inc., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Community Health Association (*), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Community Health Care Center Plan, Inc., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Community Health Foundation, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - D (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dearing, Walter P., 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dixon, James P., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Eden, Philip, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - F (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fairley, Lincoln, 1950, 1964, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Falk, Leslie A., 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fitzgibbon, J.P., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fleming, Willard C., 1957-1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Foundation for Medical Care of San Joanquin County, 1957, 1960, 1973
    See: box 2, folder 31
    See: box 3, folder 68
  - Frankel John M., 1957, 1960, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - G (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Garbarino, Joseph, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gerould, M. Lyman, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Goldblatt, Louis, 1956, 1964, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Goodenough, Benton H. (*), 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Group Health Association (Box 1, Folder 27)
    See also: Pocahontas Y. Ashe, box 1, folder 3
    See also: Walter F. Dearing, box 1, folder 18
    See also: John J. Gunther, box 1, folder 24
    See also: Dorothy McCamman, box 2, folder 49
    See also: George Perrott, box 3, folder 53
    See also: Louis J. Segadelli, box 3, folder 65
  - Groups Health Association: Personnel record, 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Group Health Association: personnel record, 1972-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Group Health Cooperative of Puget Sound (*), 1962-1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - H (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Harrington, Donald C., 1959-1970 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York (*), 1963-1970 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Hicks, Otho J., 1955, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Hunt, Andrew D., 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU)
    See: box 1, folder 5
    See: box 1, folder 8
    See: box 1, folder 22
    See: box 1, folder 25
    See: box 2, folder 44
    See: box 2, folder 50
  - ILWU locals, 1953, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - ILWU Benefit Funds
    See: box 2, folder 34
  - ILWU-PMA Negotiating Committee: minutes, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - ILWU-PMA Welfare Fund, 1963, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    See also: box 2, folder 51
    See also: box 3, folder 72
  - ILWU-PMA Welfare Fund: Personnel record, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - ILWU-PWA Welfare Fund: travel vouchers, 1955-1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - J-K (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Kagel, Sam, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Kaiser Foundation Health Plan (*), 1963-1970 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - Kaiser Foundation Health Plan, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    See also: box 3, folder 70
    See also: box 3, folder 76
  - Kaiser Foundation Hospitals, Oakland
    See: box 2, folders 37-38
  - Kaiser Foundation Hospitals, Portland, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Kappa Systems, Inc., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Kay, Raymond, 1962-1975 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Keene, Clifford, H.
  - Kerr, Lorin E. (*), 1960-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Kibre, Jeff, 1952-1964 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Kibre, Pearl (Mrs. Jeff), 1964 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Klem, Margaret C., 1956, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - L (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Lamb, Richard, 1963, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Letson, Edward W. (*), 1961, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Letson, Edward W., 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Locke, Ben Z., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - M (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - McCamman, Dorothy, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - McCarthy, Denis J. (*), 1966-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - McElrath, A.Q., 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Massachusetts Mutual Insurance Company, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Melnikow, Henry, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Mori, Hazel, 1961, 1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Mount zion Hospital, 1961, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - N (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - National Institutes on Rehabilitation and Health Services, 1961, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - National Rehabilitation Association, Western Regional Conference, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Neiman, Irwin S., 1963 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Northwest Regional Institute on Rehabilitation and Labor Health Services, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - P (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Pacific Maritime Association (Box 3, Folder 53)
    See: Wallace L.C. Brown, box 1, folder 8
    See: M. Lyman Gerould, box 1, folder 25
    See: Benton H. Goodenough, box 1, folder 26
    See: Denis J. McCarthy, box 2, folder 49
    See: J. Paul St. Sure, box 3, folder 63
    See: K.F. Saysette, box 3, folder 63
  - Pacific Maritime Association, Washington Area, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Pacific National Life Assurance Company, 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    See also: box 3, folder 58
    See also: box 3, folder 59
  - "Paul", 1943, 1959 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Pearson, David A., 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Pelton, Walter J. (*), 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Pelton, Walter J., 1962-1968 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Physicians News Services
    See: box 3, folder 63
  - Powell, James R., 1959-1965 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - R (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Racine, William E., 1970 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Raz, Shmuel, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Reed, Louis, 1965, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Roberts, Markley, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Robinson, James, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Rogers, Edward S., 1962 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Root, Chester L.(*), 1963-1974 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Ross, M.H., 1968, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Ross-Loos Medical Group, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - S (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - St. Sure, J. Paul (*), 1963, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - San Joaquin County Medical Society
  - San Joaquin Foundation for Medical Care
  - Sasuly, Richard, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Saysette, K.F., 1962 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Sebelius, Carl L., 1962 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Segadelli, Louis J., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Shereshefsky, Pauline M., 1963, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Siciliano, Rocco, 1966, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Silver, George A., 1964, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Somers, Anne R. (Mrs. Herman M.), 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Stevens, Harold, 1963-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Terris, Milton, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Thompson, Boyd, 1956-1959, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Tolles, Newman Arnold, Circa 1957, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Treloar, Alan, E., 1958 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Union Health Service
    See: box 1, folder 2
  - United Mine Workers of America Welfare and Retirement Fund, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    See also: box 2, folder 43
  - United States Civil Service Commission (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (*), 1963-1974 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    See also: Agnes W. Brewster, box 1, folder 7
    See also: Viron L. Diefenbach, box 1, folder 17
    See also: John M. Frankel, box 1, folder 23
    See also: Joseph V. Hunt, box 2, folder 30
    See also: Elliot H. Pennell, box 3, folder 53
    See also: Walter J. Pelton, box 3, folder 55
  - Van Goor, Robert E., 1959, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Van Goor, Wanda (Mrs. Robert E.), 1964 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Vohs, James A., 1964-1974 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - W (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Wallin, Ira O., 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Watters, Frank C., 1966-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Waybur, Anne (*), 1953, 1956, 1962-1963 March (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Waybur, Anne, (*) (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Waybur, Anne: memoranda to locals, 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Weinerman, E. Richard, 1960, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Weissman, Arthur (*), 1961-1969 (Box 3, Folder 76)